Thibaut GERMAIN

☐ +33 6 89 49 29 21 | thibaut.germain@ens-paris-saclay.fr | thibaut-germain.github.io thibaut-germain | thibaut-germain

Paris, France

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie at the crossroads between geometry, shape analysis, and machine learning for time series. More precisely, I am interested in developing shape-based machine learning methods for time series with a particular focus on biomedical applications.

EDUCATION

2021 - now	Ph.D., Centre Borelli, Ecole Normale Supérieur Paris-saclay, France. Thesis focusing on Pattern de-
	tection and shape analysis for physiological time series. Supervised by Laurent OUDRE and Charles TRUONG
2020	Master of Science , Ecole Normale Supérieur Paris-saclay , France . Master Mathématiques Vision et Apprentissage (MVA), highest honors.
2017	Master of Science, Université Lyon 1, France. Master Operational Research and Supply Chain.
2017	Master's degree, Ecole des Mines de Saint-Etienne, France. Master in supply chain engineering.

Positions

2024	Visiting researcher, Duke University, Durham, NC (USA). One month visiting.
2020	Research volunteer, Centre Borelli, France . Assisted Argyris KALOGERATOS for simulating COVID-19 dynamical propagation within a hospital department. Four months volunteering.
2017 - 2019	Supply chain engineer, Tempest Tech Corp., Fresno, CA (USA) . Standardizing and optimizing operational activities. Overseeing research and development activities. Management support: supervising the production team, training, and hiring.
2017	Supply chain intern, Airbus Helicopters, Marignane, France . Modeling and optimizing the supply chain of the H160 during its research and development phase. Evaluating the supply chain robustness through a sensitivity analysis.

TEACHING

2021 - 2024 Teaching assistant (1D/11), Ecole Normale Superieur Fairs-saciay, France.	2021 - 2024	Teaching assistant (TD/TP), Ecole Normale Supérieur Paris-saclay, France.
---	-------------	---

- Mathematical statistics and machine learning, (Graduate course).
- Statistics for the French exam "Agrégation de mathématiques", (Graduate course).

2022 Teaching assistant (TD/TP), Ecole Normale Supérieur Paris-saclay, France.

• Introduction to measure theory, integration, and probability, (Undergraduate course).

STUDENTS

Graduate

- Valerio GUERRINI, M2 MVA, April-September 2024, co-supervised with Charles TRUONG and Laurent OUDRE, on "Benchmark for motif discovery in time series".
- Lucas HAUBERT, M2 MVA, April-September 2024, co-supervised with Chrysoula KOSMA and Laurent OUDRE, on "Toward shape-based losses for deep learning on time series".

Undergraduate

- Romain DELAUNAY and Hugo GAIBLE, L3 ENS Paris Saclay, April-June 2023, co-supervised with Alexandre BOIS and Laurent OUDRE, on "Convolutional dictionnay learning".
- William RAMOS and Oussama ZEKRI, L3 ENS Paris Saclay, April-June 2022, co-supervised with Laurent OUDRE, on "Optimal transport and elastic measures on time series".

TALKS

- 1. "Shape analysis and machine learning for time series", (Duke University, July 2024).
- 2. "Persistence-based Motifs Discovery in Time Series", (Centre Borelli, June 2024).
- 3. "Linear-trend normalization for multivariate subsequence similarity search", (ICDE 2024, May 2024).
- 4. "Interpretable classification of ventilation behaviors based on machine learning", (Integrative Neuroscience and Cognitive Center (INCC), January 2023).
- 5. "Une méthode de regroupement des comportements respiratoires basée sur des distances DTW entre séries temporelle & Comment les nouveaux outils permettent de redécouvrir des données ?", (Maths & Medecine, December 2022).
- 6. "Unsupervised study of plethysmography signals through DTW clustering", (EMBC 2022, July 2022).

PUBLICATIONS

Journal papers:

- 1. Thibaut Germain, Charles Truong, and Laurent Oudre. "Persistence-based motif discovery in time series". In: *IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering* (2024)
- 2. Thibaut Germain et al. "Unsupervised classification of plethysmography signals with advanced visual representations". In: *Frontiers in Physiology* 14 (2023), p. 1154328

International conference papers:

- 1. Thibaut Germain et al. "Shape analysis for time series". In: Advances in neural information processing systems (2024)
- Thibaut Germain, Charles Truong, and Laurent Oudre. "Interactive motif discovery in time series with persistent homology". In: Joint European Conference on Machine Learning and Knowledge Discovery in Databases. Springer. 2024, pp. 383–387
- 3. Thibaut Germain, Charles Truong, and Laurent Oudre. "Linear-trend normalization for multivariate subsequence similarity search". In: 2024 IEEE 40th International Conference on Data Engineering Workshops (ICDEW). IEEE. 2024, pp. 167–175
- 4. Thibaut Germain et al. "Unsupervised study of plethysmography signals through DTW clustering". In: 2022 44th Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine & Biology Society (EMBC). IEEE. 2022, pp. 3396–3400

National conference papers:

- 1. Thibaut Germain et al. "Détection non supervisée de motifs sur séries temporelles". In: 2023 29ème Colloque Francophone de Traitement du Signal et des Images (GRETSI). 2023
- 2. Thibaut Germain et al. "Approches non-supervisées et non-linéaires pour l'analyse de signaux de pléthysmographie". In: 2022 28ème Colloque Francophone de Traitement du Signal et des Images (GRETSI). 2022

REFERENCES

1. Laurent OUDRE

Full Professor, Machine Learning Department Centre Borelli, Ecole Normale Supérieur Paris-Saclay

Email: laurent.oudre@ens-paris-saclay.fr

Phone: +33 1 81 87 53 96 Relationship: Ph.D. supervisor

2. Eric KREJCI

Research Director, Neurophysiology Department Centre Borelli, Ecole Normale Supérieur Paris-Saclay

Email: krejcier@gmail.com Phone: +33 1 42 86 41 16 Relationship: Colleague